Will Barker Papers
Will Barker Papers
1852-1970
Barker, Will.
19.0 linear ft.
American author, native of Troy, New York, who wrote a number of books about animals, some for young adults. Collection contains correspondence (1852-1970), business, personal, and family; book manscripts and galleys; genealogical material relating to the Barker family; scrapbooks; memorabilia, including calendars and photographs; and published material, including articles and pamphlets.
148832
Biographical History
Will Barker (1908-?) was an American author from Troy, New York. Following his military service, he enrolled in the Veterans Authors Workshop which started him on a career as a full-time writer. In addition to several natural history books for children and numerous articles, he wrote for the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (1949-1954) and edited books for the New York Times Book Review. He also lectured, appeared at children's book fairs, did the photography and illustrations for his own books, and taught seminars at writing workshops. He received awards from the National Wildlife Federation for his work in conservation education.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Will Barker Papers consist of corespondence, writings, published material and memorabilia.
Correspondence has both business and personal letters dating from 1852 to 1970.
Writings contains material for five nature books, several articles, and lectures for school and writing workshops. Also included is some of Barker's editing work.
Published material includes mainly books, magazines and newspapers.
Memorabilia contains photographs, scrapbooks, personal papers, material on family history, and a small amount of Masonic papers.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. All other series are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- Children's; Barker, Will.; Barker family.; Animal behavior.; Authors, American.; Conservation of natural resources -- Juvenile literature.; Freemasons -- United States.; Zoology -- Juvenile literature.; Articles.; Book reviews.; Calendars (documents); Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Genealogies (histories); Manuscripts for publication.; Memorabilia.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Business, 1955-1970; undated; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Personal, 1852-1970; undated; 6 folders (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Books
    - Familiar Animals of America
      - Typescripts, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Galleys (Box 2)
    - Familiar Insects of America
      - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      - Typescripts, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Galley (Box 3)
    - Familiar Reptiles and Amphibians of America
      - Correspondence, 1961-1964 (Box 3)
      - Discarded passages from original typescript (Box 3)
      - Revised typescript (Box 3)
      - Typescript, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Typescript, author's copy (Box 3)
      - Revisions for final typescript (Box 3)
      - Galleys, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Typescripts (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Wildlife in America's History
      - Paste-ups, 4 folders (Box 4)
      - Advertising (Box 4)
    - Winter-Sleeping Wildlife
      - Correspondence, typescripts (Box 4)
      - Typescripts (Box 4)
      - Galley (Box 4)
    - Flight to Granada
      - Proposal (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Reviews and advertising, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Articles
    - Revised Book of Knowledge, correspondence and typescripts (Box 5)
    - Birds in Our Lives, "Tales Once Told", prospectus and advertising (Box 5)
    - Published, miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Typescripts of published articles (Box 5)
    - Typescripts of other articles (Box 5)
  - Pamphlets
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Editing of other's work
    - Miscellaneous typescripts (Box 5)
  - Speeches
    - Miscellaneous tapes (Box 5)
- Published material
  - Books
    - Miscellaneous, 7 volumes (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 19 volumes (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 21 volumes (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 24 volumes (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 23 volumes (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 22 volumes (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 24 volumes (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 8 volumes (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 32,000 Hours a Year, and, Roosevelt Campobello International Park; 2 volumes (Oversize 1)
  - Magazines
    - Miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 7 issues (Oversize 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 14 issues (Oversize 2)
  - Pamphlets
    - General, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - General, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Book lists, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Historic Preservation, 1957-1965; 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Historic Preservation, 1966; 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Articles
    - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - Newspapers
    - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous (Oversize 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Activities (Box 15)
  - Biographical (Box 15)
  - Books, 8 volumes (Box 17)
  - Books, 14 volumes (Box 16)
  - Calendars, 1958-1966 (Box 15)
  - Calendars, 2 items (Oversize 2)
  - Conservation pledge, 500 cards (Box 15)
  - Invitations (Box 15)
  - Masonic papers in leather case (Box 16)
  - Newspapers (Box 17)
  - Personal papers, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Photographs, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Scrapbooks, 2 volumes (Oversize 3)
  - Scrapbooks, 2 volumes (Oversize 4)